<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe discourse of a disease called the suffocation of the mother Written vppon occasion which hath beene of late taken thereby, to suspect possesion of an euill spirit, or some such like supernaturall power. Wherin is declared that diuers strange actions and passions of the body of man, which in the common opinion, are imputed to the diuell, haue their true naturall causes, and do accompanie this disease. By Edvvard Iorden Doctor in Physicke.</title>
            <author>Jorden, Edward, 1569-1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04663</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14790</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119360</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854567</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854567</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19994</idno>
            <availability>
               <p n="P2">This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. Searching, reading, printing, or downloading EEBO-TCP texts is reserved for the authorized users of these project partner institutions. Permission must be granted for subsequent distribution, in print or electronically, of this EEBO-TCP Phase II text, in whole or in part.</p>
               <p n="P1">This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>   
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English Books Online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP; phase 2, no. A04663)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online; image set 19994)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 757:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe discourse of a disease called the suffocation of the mother Written vppon occasion which hath beene of late taken thereby, to suspect possesion of an euill spirit, or some such like supernaturall power. Wherin is declared that diuers strange actions and passions of the body of man, which in the common opinion, are imputed to the diuell, haue their true naturall causes, and do accompanie this disease. By Edvvard Iorden Doctor in Physicke.</title>
                  <author>Jorden, Edward, 1569-1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 25 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Windet, dwelling at the signe of the Crosse Keyes at Powles Wharfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of the suffocation of the mother.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
               <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
               <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
               <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
               <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
               <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
               <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;GAP&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
               <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
               <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hysteria --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19994:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19994:1"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVRSE OF A DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>EASE CALLED THE Suffocation of the Mother.</p>
            <p>Written vppon occaſion which hath beene of late taken thereby, to ſuſpect poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion of an euill ſpirit, or ſome ſuch like ſupernaturall power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherin is declared that diuers ſtrange</hi> actions and paſsions of the body of man, which in <hi>the common opinion, are imputed to the Diuell, haue their true naturall cauſes, and do accompanie this diſeaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By EDVVARD IORDEN <hi>Doctor in Phyſicke.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <q>FOR THOV SHALT LABOR</q>
               <q>PEACE PLENTIE</q>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON.</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Iohn Windet,</hi> dwelling at the Signe of <hi>the Croſſe Keyes at Powles Wharfe.</hi> 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19994:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19994:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull the Preſident and Fellowes of the <hi>Colledge of Phiſitions in</hi> London.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I am deſirous to ſatiſfie all indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent men concerning the occaſion and intent of this my diſcourſe: ſo I thought good to direct the ſame eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially vnto this ſocietie, whereof I am a member; to teſtifie both how iustly or rather neceſsarily I haue beene drawn to the vndertaking and publiſhing hereof: as alſo how willing I am to ſubmit my ſelfe to your learned cenſure; the argument of my writing being ſuch as none can better iudge of then your ſelues.</p>
            <p>And firſt I protest vpon that credit which I deſire to haue among you, that I haue not vndertaken this buſineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of mine owne accord, as if I eſteemed of mine owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and obſeruation in this caſe aboue other mens. For (if it had beene thought good to haue impoſed it vppon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) I do acknowledge that there are many among vs better able then my ſelfe to haue written in this kind, vnto whome I would willingly haue put ouer my taske. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did I euer find my ſelfe prouoked hereunto vpon any
<pb facs="tcp:19994:3"/>peeuiſh humor to contradict or to diſgrace any who doe iudge otherwiſe of ſome pointes contained herein, then my ſelfe doe: many of them being ſuch as I do loue and affect well. Neither vpon any fawning humor to pleaſe or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any perſon whatſoeuer; which I doe eſteeme more baſe then begging. But diſclayming both hony and gall, I haue plainely ſet downe the true doctrine of Phiſicke concerning that diſeaſe which giues ſo great occaſion of diſtraction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many good men: eſpecially ſuch as haue not le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rning ſufficient to reſolue them of this point, or not that modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and humilitie of ſpirit to acknowledge their inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie, and to hearken vnto others whom in all reaſon they might thinke able to direct them better in ſuch a caſe.</p>
            <p>For if it be true that one man cannot be perfect in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery arte and profeſsion, and therefore in caſes out of our owne callings, we do depend vpon thoſe which haue beene trayned vp in other particular ſubiects, beleeuing men in their owne profeſsions: Why ſhould we not prefer the iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments of Phiſitions in a queſtion concerning the actions and paſsions of mans bodie (the proper ſubiect of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion) before our owne conceites; as we do the opinions of Diuines, Lawyers, Artificers, &amp;c. in their proper Elements. Neither haue I done this as taking vpon me to reforme the mindes of men which are not vnder my charge (for I could willingly haue permitted euery man to enioy his owne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion:) But being a Phiſition, and iudging in my conſcience that theſe matters haue beene miſtaken by the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; I thought good to make knowne the doctrine of this diſeaſe, ſo farre forth, as may be in a vulgar tongue conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently diſcloſed, to the end that the vnlearned and raſh conceits of diuers, might be thereby brought to better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:19994:3"/>and moderation; who are apt to make euery thing a ſupernaturall work which they do not vnderſtand, proportioning the bounds of nature vnto their own capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: which might proue an occaſion of abuſing the name of God, and make vs to vſe holy prayer as vngroundedly as the Papiſts do their prophane trickes; who are readie to drawe forth their wooden dagger, if they do but ſee a maid or woman ſuffering one of theſe fits of the Mother, coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and exorciſing them as if they were poſſeſſed with euil ſpirits. And for want of worke, will oftentimes ſuborne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that are in health, to counterfait ſtrange motions and behauiours: as I once ſaw in the <hi>Santo</hi> in <hi>Padua</hi> fiue or ſixe at one ſermon interrupting and reuiling the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, vntill he had put them to ſilence by the ſigne of the Croſſe, and certaine powerleſſe ſpelles.</p>
            <p>Wherefore it behoueth vs as to be zealous in the truth, ſo to be wiſe in diſcerning truth from counterfaiting and naturall cauſes from ſupernaturall power. I doe not deny but that God doth in theſe dayes-worke extraordinarily, for the deliuerance of his children, and for other endes beſt knowne vnto himſelfe; and that among other, there may be both poſſeſsions by the Diuell, and obſeſsions and witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, &amp;c. and diſpoſſeſsion alſo through the Prayers and ſupplications of his ſeruants, which is the onely meanes left vnto vs for our reliefe in that caſe. But ſuch examples be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verie rare now adayes, I would in the feare of God ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe men to be very circumſpect in pronouncing of a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion: both becauſe the impostures be many, and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of naturall diſeaſes be ſtrange to ſuch as haue not loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked throughly into them.</p>
            <p>But let vs conſider a little the ſignes which ſome doe
<pb facs="tcp:19994:4"/>ſhew of a ſupernaturall power in theſe examples. For if they ſay there neede no ſuch ſignes appeare, becauſe the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill by witchcraft may inflict a naturall diſeaſe: then I ask them what they haue to doe with the Diuell, or with diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsing of him, when he is not their preſent, but hath beene onely an externall cauſe of a diſeaſe, by kindling or corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the humours of our bodies; which diſeaſe as well as other will ſubmit it ſelfe to phyſicall indications: as is ſhewed, cap. <hi>1.</hi> Wherefore they muſt needes make him to be an internall cauſe, and to poſſeſſe the members and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the bodie, and holde them to his vſe: or elſe they vnderſtand not what they ſay, when they doe peremptorily diſclaime naturall meanes, and auouch that they ſpeake certaine wordes, and performe certaine voluntarie motions vpon his incitation, and are hindred by him from ſpeaking other wordes which they would faine vtter. And therefore to this end diuerſe ſignes and Symptoms are alledged by them, as arguments of a ſupernaturall and extraordinarie power inhaerent in the body.</p>
            <p>One of their ſignes is <hi>Inſenſibilitie,</hi> when they doe not feele, being pricked with a pin, or burnt with fire, &amp;c. Is this ſo ſtrange a ſpectacle, when in the Palſie, the falling ſickeneſse, Apoplexis, and diuerſe other diſeaſes, it is dayly obſerued? And in theſe fits of the Mother it is ſo ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie as I neuer read any Authour writing of this diſeaſe who doth not make mention thereof. This poynt you ſhall finde proued both by authorities and examples in the <hi>4.</hi> Chapter.</p>
            <p>There alſo you ſhall find conuulſions, contractions, diſtortions, and ſuch like to be ordinarie Symptoms in this diſeaſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19994:4"/>
            <p>Another ſigne of a ſupernaturall power they make to be the due &amp; orderly returning of the fits, when they keepe their iuſt day and houre, which we call periods or cicuits. This accident as it is common to diuerſe other chronicall diſeaſes, as head-aches, gowtes, Epilepſies, Tertians, Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, &amp;c. ſo it is often obſerued in this diſeaſe of the mother as is ſufficiently proued in the <hi>2.</hi> Chapter.</p>
            <p>Another argumnt of theirs is the offence in eating, or drinking, as if the Diuell ment to choake them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. But this Symptom is alſo ordinarie in vterin affects, as I ſhew in the ſixt Chapter: and I haue at this time a patient troubled in like maner.</p>
            <p>Another reaſon of their is, the comming of the fits vpon the preſence of ſome certaine perſon. The like I doe ſhew in the ſame Chapter, and the reaſons of it, from the ſtirring of the affections of the mind.</p>
            <p>Another maine argument of theirs, is the deliuerance vpon faſting and prayer: which we will imagin to be ſo in deed, without any counterfeiting in that point. You ſhall ſee in the <hi>7.</hi> Chapter, how this may be a naturall remedie two maner of wayes: the one by pulling downe the pride of the bodie, and the height of the naturall humors therof; a verie conuenient meanes, and often preſcribed by our Authours in yong and luſtie bodies: the other by the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſwaſion of the patient to find releaſe by that means: which I ſhew in that Chapter by rules and authorities in our profeſsion and alſo by examples, to be a verie effectuall remedie in curing diuerſe diſeaſes of this nature.</p>
            <p>Many other ſuch like inſtances they may produce, according vnto euerie ones ſeuerall conceit: which were in vaine for me to repeate perticularly: vnleſſe I knew where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:19994:5"/>they would principally inſiſt. But in the diſcourſe follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing I haue as neare as I could deſcribed al the Symptoms of this diſeaſe; whereby euerie man may readily find an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to his ſeuerall obiections.</p>
            <p>Now to teſtifie my loue and affection to this ſocietie of ours, and that I eſteeme more of the cenſure of a fewe learned and graue men, then of the opinions of a multitude of other people: I thought good to chooſe no other perſons to patronize this ſlender diſcourſe then your ſelues, who are beſt able of any in this land, or any ſuch like ſocietie elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where (that euer I could find) to iudge whether I write true doctrine or no.</p>
            <p>Wherefore deſiring you to accept it in good part, and as occaſion may ſerue to giue teſtimonie vnto it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as your iudgements and conſciences ſhall lead you, I take my leaue this <hi>2.</hi> Martii, <hi>1602.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your louing friend and Colleague.</hi> Ed. Iorden.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19994:5"/>
            <head>Of the ſuffocation of <hi>the Mother.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cap. 1.</hi> That this diſeaſe doth oftentimes giue occaſion vnto ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and vnlearned people, to ſuſpect poſſeſsion, witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, or ſome ſuch like ſupernaturall cauſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE paſsiue condition of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mankind is ſubiect vnto more diſeaſes and of other<note n="a" place="margin">Hyppocrat. <hi>6</hi> vulgar part. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> ſortes and natures then men are: and eſpecially in regarde of that part<note n="b" place="margin">Galen <hi>6.</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum affect. cap. <hi>5.</hi> radix ſuffocationum vter us.</note> from whence this diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eaſe which we ſpeake of doth ariſe. For as it hath more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of<note n="c" place="margin">Mercatus de muliebr. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1.</hi> Ad ſui ipſius alimoniam.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2.</hi> Ad ſpeciei propagationem</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3.</hi> Ad benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium indiuidui per euacuatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuperfluitatum.</item>
                     </list>
                  </note> offices belonging vnto it then other partes of the bodie haue, and accordingly is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied from other partes with whatſoeuer it hath need of for thoſe vſes: ſo it muſt needes thereby be ſubiect vnto mo infirmities then other parts are: both by reaſon of ſuch as are bred in the part it ſelfe, and alſo by reaſon of ſuch as are communicated vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it from other parts, with which it hath corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence.
<pb facs="tcp:19994:6"/>And as thoſe offices in their proper kindes are more excellent then other; ſo the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes whereby they are hurt or depraued, are more grieuous. But amongeſt all the diſeaſes wherevnto that ſex is obnoxious, there is none comparable vnto this which is called <hi>The Suffocation of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> either for varietie, or for ſtrangeneſſe of acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. For whatſoeuer ſtraunge accident may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in any of the principall functions of mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, either animall, vitall, or naturall, the ſame is to bee ſeene in this diſeaſe, by reaſon of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie and conſent which this part hath with the braine,<note place="margin">Altomarus de medend. hum. corp. malis cap. <hi>110.</hi> Barth. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagnana Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilto. <hi>226.</hi>
                  </note> heart, and liuer, the principall ſeates of theſe three functions; and the eaſie paſſage which it hath vnto them by the Vaines, Arteries, and Nerues. And whatſoeuer humor in other partes may cauſe extraordinarie affects, by reaſon of the abundance or corruption of it, this part will afford the like in as plentifull a manner, and in as high a degree of corruption: and with this aduauntage that whereas in the other, ſome one or two of the, faculties onely one are hurt (as in <hi>Apoplexies, Epilep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyes, Syncopyes,</hi> ſubuerſions of the ſtomacke, &amp;c.) and not all (vnleſſe as in <hi>Syncopyes</hi> by conſent, where the vitall function ceaſing, all the reſt muſt needes ſuffer; not as one may do from another, but all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly from this one fountaine, in ſuch ſort as you ſhall often tymes perceyue in one and the ſame perſon diuerſe accidents of contrarie natures to concurre at once.<note place="margin">Mercatus lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19994:6"/>
               <p>And hereupon the <hi>Symptoms</hi> of this diſeaſe are ſayd to be monſtrous and terrible to beholde, and of ſuch a varietie as they can hardly be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within any method or boundes. Inſomuch as they which are ignorant of the ſtrange affects which naturall cauſes may produce, and of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold examples which our profeſſion of Phiſicke doth miniſter in this kind,<note place="margin">Valetius ſcofe fing at their ignorance cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe a kind of diuell. <hi>in Holler. cap. 59.</hi>
                  </note> haue ſought aboue the Moone for ſupernaturall cauſes: aſcribing theſe accidents either to diabolicall poſſeſsion, to witch-craft, or to the immediate finger of the Almightie.</p>
               <p>But it is no maruell though the common people and men alſo in other faculties verie excellent may bee deceyued by the rareneſſe and ſtraungeneſſe of theſe matters, which are hidden out of their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon amongeſt the deepeſt myſteries of our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: when as Phiſitions themſelues,<note place="margin">Coſmocrit. li. <hi>1</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi> pag. <hi>153</hi> Inexperto me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dico ſapéſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem numi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis prabuerunt</note> as <hi>Cornelius Gemma</hi> teſtifieth. If they bee not verie wel exerciſed in the practiſe of their profeſsion, are oftentimes deceyued, imagining ſuch manifolde ſtraunge acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents as their hee mencioneth to accompanie this diſeaſe, (as <hi>ſuffocation</hi> in the throate, croaking of Frogges, hiſsing of Snakes, crowing of Cockes, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Dogges, garring of Crowes, frenzies, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions, hickcockes, laughing, ſinging, weeping, crying, &amp;c.) to proceede from ſome metaphyſicall power, when in deede (as hee there ſayeth) they are meerely naturall.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fen.</hi> 21, 3 <hi>cap:</hi> 26: <hi>tract:</hi> 4:</note> 
                  <hi>Auicen</hi> alſo in his Chapter of this diſeaſe, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the cauſes of it, ſayth, that there were ſome wiſe Phiſitions in his time which ſaid, that the cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:19994:7"/>of this diſeaſe was vnknowne: Becauſe as <hi>Iacobus de Partibus</hi> expoundeth it, they did thinke it to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted from aboue, yet notwithſtanding he ſetteth downe naturall cauſes of it, and a naturall cure.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. de morbo ſacro in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipio.</note> 
                  <hi>Hippocrates</hi> alſo long before finding this error to bee helde by ſome in his time maketh mention of diuerſe of theſe <hi>Symptoms,</hi> and ſayeth, that hee doth not ſee anie thing in them more ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, or more to bee admired, then there is in Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and Quartans, and other kindes of diſeaſes: imputing it either vnto ignorance, and want of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that Phiſitians of his time did iudge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; or vnto a worſer humor, when as beeing loath to bewray their owne defects through pride and arrogancie:<note place="margin">Inſcitiae palliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maleficium &amp; incantatio. R. Sc: li. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> and not knowing what to preſcribe would flie vnto diuine cauſes, and neglecting na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall meanes for their reliefe, would wholy relie vpon expiations, incantations, ſacrifices, &amp;c. cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their ignoraunce vnder theſe ſhadows, and pretending both more knowledge, and more pietie then other men: by which courſe they gained this aduauntage, that if the patient chanced to recouer, they ſhould bee highly renowmed for their skill; if not, their excuſe was readie that Gods hande was againſt them.</p>
               <p>This hee ſpeaketh of the Phiſitions of his time, whome he confuteth principally by two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which may ſerue for excellent rules for all men to diſcerne ſuch caſes by. The firſt is, that there is no ſupernaturall Character in theſe <hi>Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms,</hi> as hee proueth by an induction of diuerſe of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19994:7"/>them, which in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon opinion were thought to be aboue nature: yet hee proueth to haue their naturall cauſes in the bodie of man aſwell as others haue.</p>
               <p>The ſtrength of this argument will better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare hereafter in the particular <hi>Symptoms,</hi> which we are to entreate of: where it ſhall be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that the moſt of them doe both depende vpon ſuch naturall cauſes as other diſeaſes haue in our bodies, and alſo are oftentimes mixed with other diſeaſes which are accompted naturall.</p>
               <p>It may likewiſe appeare by this, that whereas all other diſeaſes are knowne by their notes and ſignes which reſemble their cauſe (as <hi>Choller, Flegme, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, &amp;c.</hi> haue their proper markes, corruption and putrefaction, their proper notes and malignity his Character) ſo there muſt be ſome Character or note of a ſupernaturall power in theſe caſes (as<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk. 8.27.28. &amp;c.</hi> Ternel de abdi tis rerum cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis lib. 2 cap 16 Platerus de me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tis alienat. pag. 102. Beniuenius de abditis morbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cauſis cap. 8. Alſharauius. C. de Epilepſia.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ſtrength or knowledge or ſuffering) or elſe we haue no cauſe but to thinke them naturall. If the diuell as an externall cauſe, may inflict a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe by ſtirring vp or kindling the humors of our bodies, and then depart without ſupplying conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall ſupernaturall power vnto it;<note n="b" place="margin">Auicen. C. de melancholiſi conting at a De monio ſufficit nobis quod conuert at comptexionem ad choleram nigram, &amp;c. vide Iacobum de partibus inhunc locum. Valeſius meth; medendi lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> then the diſeaſe is but naturall, and will ſubmit it ſelfe vnto Phyſicall cure. For externall cauſes when they are already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted, giue no indication of any remedy.</p>
               <p>The ſecond argument of this is, that theſe <hi>Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms</hi> do yeeld vnto natural cauſes, and are both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured
<pb facs="tcp:19994:8"/>and alſo eaſed by ſuch ordinary meanes, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſeaſes are: and<note n="c" place="margin">Fernel loco ci tato matheus de Grad. ex A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zariuio. C. de E pilepſia.</note> therefore they muſt needs be naturall.</p>
               <p>The ſtrength of this argument is grounded vpon the very foundation of our profeſsion which hath beene layd by<note n="d" place="margin">Hippo. de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura humaaa circa medium. Deſtatibus pau lo poſt principix um.</note> 
                  <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">Gal. de vena ſectione aduerſus Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtr: cap: <hi>8,</hi> in arte medicina li cap: <hi>8 9.</hi> in conſtitutione artis cap; <hi>13.</hi> methodi med: lib. <hi>9.10.11.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Gallen</hi> long agoe and euer ſince confirmed by the practiſe and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations of all learned men; that diſeaſes are cured by their contraries. I ſay contrary<note n="f" place="margin">Valeſius meth. med: lib: <hi>1.</hi> cap: <hi>4:</hi>
                  </note> both vnto the diſeaſe, vnto the cauſe, and vnto the <hi>Symptom.</hi> And the more exact the contrarietie is; the more proper is the remedy: as when they are equall in<note n="g" place="margin">Mercatus meth med: pag: <hi>42: 43:</hi> Gal. Simp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licium lib. <hi>3:</hi> cap: <hi>11:</hi> Valeſi us controuerſ: lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>4 Luk, 11. verſ. 21.22.</hi>
                  </note> degree or in power. But what equality of contrariety ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in degree or in power, can there be betweene a ſupernaturall ſuffocating power, and the compreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the belly or throate. They are diſperats in Logicke, but not contraries. For contrarietie is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſuch as are comprehended vnder one ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. And where one is oppoſed vnto one alone, and not indifferently vnto many. Neither doe I thinke, that any man wel aduiſed, will ſay that by compreſsion of thoſe parts, he is able to ſuppreſſe the power of the diuell. The like may be ſaide of the application of cupping glaſſes, of ſweete plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, of ligatures, &amp;c. beneath, and of euell ſmelles aboue; by all which we do obſerue thoſe kindes of fits to be mitigated: and yet there can bee no ſuch contrary reſpect in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt a ſupernatural cauſe, as is between a remedy and a diſeaſe. They are alſo procured vpon ſweete ſmelles, vpon pleaſant meats and drinkes, vpon feare, anger, iealouſie, &amp;c. as in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19994:8"/>particular cauſes ſhall bee farther declared: and yet no ſuch conſent can bee ſhewed in them with any ſupernaturall affect, as that they may any way cauſe or encreaſe it. Wherefore the rule of <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> muſt needesbe true; that if theſe <hi>Symptoms</hi> do yeeld vnto naturall remedies, they muſt alſo bee naturall themſelues. And thus much in explanation of theſe two arguments of <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> againſt the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of his time: which notwithſtanding hath been continued in the mindes of men vntill this day, and no maruell: vnleſſe the ſame corruption which bred it at the firſt, had beene remoued out of the world. And therefore diuers of our Authors doe make eſpeciall mention of this caſe wherein they report the common people to haue beene deceiued by imagining witchcraft or poſſeſſion,<note place="margin">Georg. Godel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. de magis &amp;c. lib <hi>1.</hi> cap <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there was none.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amatus Luſitanus</hi> reporteth of one <hi>Diua Clara,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bruno Seideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us de morbis incurab: pag: <hi>29</hi> Centuria <hi>5,</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat: <hi>78.</hi>
                  </note> a maide of 18. yeares of age, which had euery day two or three ſuch ſtrange fits, as thoſe that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her, gaue out that that ſhe was haunted with an euill ſpirit.</p>
               <p>In thoſe fits euery part of her body was diſtorted, ſhe felt nothing, nor perceiued any thing: but had all her ſences benummed, her hart beating, her teeth cloſe ſhut together: yet for an houres ſpace or two ſhe would haue ſuch ſtrong motions, that ſhee would weary the ſtrongeſt men that came at her. When ſhe had beene three weekes in this caſe, her left arme began to be reſolued with a palſie, &amp;c. He being called vnto her preſcribed ſuch remedies as
<pb facs="tcp:19994:9"/>are vſuall in this caſe, and within few dayes recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her, to the great admiration of the beholders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petrus Forrestus</hi> maketh mention of another maid of 22.<note place="margin">Obſeruationu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> medicin: lib: <hi>10</hi> obſeru: <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> yeares old, which dwelt with a Burgermaſter of <hi>Delft</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> who falling in loue with a yong man, fell alſo into theſe fits of the Mother: which held her many houres together with ſuch violent horrible accidents, as hee neuer ſawe the like: her whole body being pulled to and fro with convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue motions, her belly ſometimes lifted vp, and ſometimes depreſſed, a roaring noiſe heard within her, with crying and howling, a diſtortion of her armes and handes: in ſomuch as thoſe about her thought her to be poſſeſſed with a diuell, and out of all hope of recouery. He being called vnto her in Ianuarie 1565. applied conuenient remedies as there he ſetteth downe, and in a ſhort time reſtored her to her health againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Thaddeaus Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus miſcall: cap <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note>Many more ſuch like examples might bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced both out of authenticall writers in our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion and out of our own experiences, which yet do liue (were it not that late examples would bee offenſiue to rehearſe:) but theſe may ſuffice to ſhow how eaſily men vnexperienced in thoſe extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie kindes of diſeaſes, may miſtake the cauſes of them: when through admiration of the vnwonted and grieuous accidents they behold, they are caried vnto Magicall and Metaphyſicall ſpeculations. But the learned Phiſition who hath firſt beene trained vp in the ſtudy of Philoſophy, and afterwards con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the practiſe and experience of all manner
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19994:9"/>of naturall diſeaſes, is beſt able to diſcerne what is naturall, what not naturall, what preternaturall, and what ſupernaturall, the three firſt being properly ſubiect to his profeſsion: and therefore they doe wrong vnto the faculty of Phiſicke, and vnto them ſelues, and oftentimes vnto others, who neglecting that light which wee might yeeld them, doe runne headlong and blinde fold into many errors and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities. For preuention whereof I haue breefly ſet downe what the doctrine of Phiſitions is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this diſeaſe of the Mother,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 28. <hi>obſern.</hi> 26.</note> which of all other is moſt ſubiect vnto miſconſtruction. For that as <hi>Forreſtus</hi> ſaieth it is a harde matter to diſcerne in what maner the Mother may occaſion ſuch ſtrange and manifold accidents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cap. 2.</hi> What this diſeaſe is, and by what meanes it cauſeth ſuch varietie of Symptoms.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His diſeaſe is called by diuerſe names amongſt our Authors.<note place="margin">Cardanus de cauſis ſig. et locis morborum cap. <hi>114.</hi> Altomarus cap. <hi>110.</hi> Guaynerie us cap. de ſuffo: matricis.</note> 
                  <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio Hyſterica, Suffocatio, Praefocatio,</hi> and <hi>Strangulatus vteri, Caducus matricis, &amp;c.</hi> In Engliſh the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or the Suffocation of the Mother,<note place="margin">Aeetius tetr: <hi>4</hi> Serm. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>68</hi> P. Aegineta lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>71</hi> Victor Trinca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel. lib: <hi>5.</hi> ſect. <hi>5</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it takes them with choaking in the throat: and it is <hi>an affect of the Mother or wombe wherein the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal parts of the bodie by conſent do ſuffer diuerſly accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:19994:10"/>to the diuerſitie of the cauſes and diſeaſes wherewith the matrix is offended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I call it an <hi>affect</hi> in a large ſignification to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend both <hi>morbum</hi> and <hi>Symptoma.</hi> For ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is either of them, and ſomtimes both. For in regard the actions of expulſion or retention in the <hi>Mother</hi> are hurt. It may be called a <hi>Symptoma in actione laeſa:</hi> in regard of the humor to be expelled which corrupteth and putrifieth to a venemous malignitie. It is likewiſe a <hi>Symptom in excremento vteri mutato.</hi> And in regard of the perfrigeration of the Mother, and ſo of the whole bodie. It is alſo a <hi>Symptom</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Albert. Botto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus cap. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>in qualitate tangibili mulata,</hi> not <hi>morbus ex inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perie:</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Gal. locorum affectorum 3. cap. 7. Petrus Salius pag. 467. Altomarus cap <hi>110.</hi> Horatius An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius Epist. 6</note> becauſe it is ſuddenly inflicted &amp; ſuddenly remoued. But in regard of the riſing of the Mother wherby it is ſomtimes drawn vpwards or ſidewards aboue his natural ſeate, compreſsing the neighbour parts, &amp; ſo conſequently one another. It may be ſaid to be <hi>morbus in ſitu,</hi> in reſpect of the compreſsion it ſelfe, cauſing ſuffocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and difficultie of breathing. It may be<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. de cauſis morb. cap. 7</note> 
                  <hi>cauſa morbi in forma</hi> by cauſing <hi>coarctati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the inſtruments of breathing. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times theſe are complicated and<note n="d" place="margin">Altom arus c<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>citate. Rondele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tius methodo curand. morb. cap. 69. mathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us de grad. in 9 Rhaſis. cap. 28</note> together with a venemous vapour, ariſing from this corrupt humor vnto diuers parts of the bodie, there will be an euill poſition of the matrix alſo: either becauſe the liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, vaines and arteries beeing obſtructed:<note n="e" place="margin">Mercatus lib <hi>2.</hi> cap 3.</note> by thoſe vapours are ſhortened of their wontedlength, and ſo draw vp the part higher then it ſhould be; or<note n="f" place="margin">Matheus de grad. in 9 Rhaſis cap. 28. Hor. Augenius ſibi offenſum fugiens vt et iucundum inſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quens.</note> for that the matrix being grieuouſly anoyed with the malignity of thoſe vapours doth contract it ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:19994:10"/>and riſe vp by a locall motion towards the midrif.</p>
               <p>I ſay of the <hi>Mother</hi> or wombe becauſe although the wombe many times in this diſeaſe doe ſuffer but ſecondarily, yet the other parts are not affected in this diſeaſe but from the Mother: <hi>(Radix ſuffocationum v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus)</hi> which finding it ſelfe anoyed by ſome vnkind humor, either within it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Galen. 6. loc. af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fert. cap. 5. Auicen. Fen. 21 3. cap. 16. tract 4. initium eſt ex matrice et) peruenit ad communitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fortem cordis et cerebri &amp;c. Horatius Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nius Epiſtola 6.</note> or in the veſſels adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or belonging vnto it, doth by a naturall inſtinct which is ingrafted in euery part of the body for his owne preſeruation, endeuour to expell that which is offenſiue: in which conflict if either the paſſage be obſtructed, or the humor inobedient or malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or the functions of the wombe any way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praued, the offence is communicated from thence vnto the reſt of the body. The principall part of the body are the ſeates of the three faculties, which do gouerne the whole body. The braine of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimall, the hart of the vitall, the liuer of the naturall; although ſome other parts are plentifully endewed with ſome of theſe faculties, as the ſtomacke, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trailes, vaines, ſpleene, &amp;c. with naturall faculties,<note n="g" place="margin">Gal. de diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultate reſpira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> di lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. 7. Trincauel. li. 4 cap. 12. Felix platerus ca. de reſpira. defectu Gal. de ſympt. differentiis Cap 2.3.</note> the inſtruments of reſpiration with animall and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall. Theſe parts are affected in this diſeaſe, and do ſuffer in their functions as they are diminiſhed, depraued, or aboliſhed,<note n="h" place="margin">Gal. 5. loc. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. 6 Mercatus pag. 173.</note> according to the nature &amp; plenty of the humor, and the temperament and ſcituation of the Mother: and that <hi>diuerſly:</hi> For ſomtimes the inſtruments of reſpiration alone doe ſuffer, ſometimes the heart alone, ſometimes two or three faculties together, ſometimes ſucceſſiuely one after another, ſometimes one part ſuffereth both
<pb facs="tcp:19994:11"/>a reſolution and a conuulſion in the ſame fit,<note place="margin">Petrus ſolius di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſus pag. 400</note> or when as it ſuffereth in one part and not in another, as we ſee oftentimes ſence and motion to bee taken away and yet hearing and memorie to remaine,<note place="margin">Mercat. pa. 170</note> the ſpeech failing and reſpiration good.<note place="margin">Merca. pa. 174</note> Sometimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, ſence, and motion do altogether faile, and yet the pulſe remaine good: So that the varietie of thoſe fits is exceeding great, wherein the principall parts of the body doe diuerſly ſuffer.</p>
               <p>Another diuerſitie there is, in the order of theſe fits: for ſometimes they keep due g periods or circuits yearly or monthly,<note place="margin">Aetius lib. 26. cap. 70 P. Agineta. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. 71. Rhaſis cont. lib. <hi>22.</hi> meſueſum. <hi>4.</hi> part. <hi>4.</hi> ſect. <hi>1</hi> cap. 8. Auicen Fen. <hi>21</hi> 3. cap. 16. tract 4. quandoque ſunt period. eius tardi, quando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que accidit om<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni die.</note> according to the falling ſicknes, and ſometime euery weeke, ſometimes h euery day, &amp;c. I know a gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this towne, who for 2. yeares together neuer miſſed a fit of the Mother in the afternoone. The like is hereafter mentioned in the Eſſex gentlewo. who for 16. years together had euery day a fit of the Mother at a certaine houre. <hi>D. Argent</hi> and I had another patient, in whome for 10. weeks together we obſerued a fit of the mother eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſaturday. I adde <hi>by conſent of the Mother</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh thoſe <hi>Symptoms</hi> or diſeaſes from ſuch as are cauſed originally by the part affected. For being pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cured but by conſent, they endure no longer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fits of the mother do continue. The conſent or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie which the matrix hath with thoſe principal parts of the body is eaſily perceiued, if wee conſider the anatomy of that part, &amp; the diuers waies wherby it may and doth communicate with them. The fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this part, beſides that which is commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all other for their nutriment deriued from the naturall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19994:11"/>facultie, are 2. the one reſpecting the preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the whole body, as it is an <hi>Emunctory</hi> of diuers ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities which do abound in that ſex.<note place="margin">Gabr. Fallopius de med. purg. Cap. 17. et 23. Via euacuatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> The other for the propagation of mankind, where it is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and nouriſhed vntill it be able to appeare in the world. In regard of theſe offices this part hath neede of great varietie of prouiſion, according as the vſes are manifold. The ſubſtance is neruous, for the great neceſſitie it hath of ſence and motion.</p>
               <p>It is alſo <hi>Porous</hi> for the better entertaining of the vitall ſpirits and the neceſſitie it hath of diſtenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and contraction.<note place="margin">Conſtant. Varo lius lib. 4. cap. <hi>3</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>It is tied vnto diuers partes of the body that it might the better beare the weight of an infant: backwards by little ſtrings vnto the lower gut,<note place="margin">Gaſparus Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hinus hiſtoria anatom. p. 71.</note> vnto the loines and <hi>os ſacrum:</hi> forwardes vnto the necke of the bladder and <hi>os pubis</hi> by certaine membranes deriued from the <hi>peritoneum:</hi> on each ſide it is tyed vnto <hi>oſsa illii</hi> by a ligament growing from the muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the loynes. It receiueth alſo for the former v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, vaines from the liuer, arteries from the hart, and nerues from the braine and backe, which are all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted into the ſubſtance of the part, to deriue vnto it the benefit of thoſe 3. faculties, both for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vſe of the part, and for the vſe of propagation and to diſcharge the whole bodie of diuers ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities, which otherwiſe would be an occaſion of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny infirmities in them.</p>
               <p>Now according to this deſcription let vs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how by conſent, the principall partes of the bodie may bee affected from the matrix.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19994:12"/>
               <p>The partes of our bodie doe ſuffer by conſent<note n="b" place="margin">Trincauel. l. <hi>3</hi> Sect. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> two manner of wayes. The one is when they doe receyue ſome offenſiue thing from another parte which is<note n="c" place="margin">Auicen. Fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>1.3.</hi> tract. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>6</hi> Montagnana conſil. <hi>226</hi>
                  </note> called <hi>Communitas non abſoluta.</hi> And this is either a qualitie as in venemous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious diſeaſes, where the malignitie creeping from one part to another doth alter the qualitie of the parts as it goeth, and at the laſt is comminica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the principall parts, as the head, heart, liuer, longs, &amp;c. or a ſubſtance which either by manifeſt conducts, as vaines, nerues, arteries, &amp;c. or by inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible pores (as <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Fernel. patho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiae li. <hi>6.</hi> ca. <hi>16</hi>
                  </note> our bodies are tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirable, and tranſmeable) is conuaied from one part to another: whether it be a vapour or a humor, as wee doe commonly obſerue in the fits offeuers, where a vapour ariſing from the part affected, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſeth it ſelfe through the whole body, and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſenſiue parts with colde or heate, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue parts with trembling, the vitall parts with fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſounding, inequalitie of pulſe, &amp;c. the naturall parts with deiection of appetite, ſubuerſion of the ſtomacke, &amp;c. vntill nature haue ouercome and diſcuſſed it. In theſe Feuers alſo many times hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors are ſo plentifully ſent vp vnto the braine,<note place="margin">Foreſtus lib. <hi>10</hi> obſeru: <hi>115:</hi> in ſcholiis.</note> as by cuſtome or long continuance they breede ſome proper affect there.</p>
               <p>The other kinde of communitie is that which they call <hi>Communitas abſoluta,</hi> wherein the part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting receiueth nothing from the other, but yet is partaker of his griefe: either for <hi>ſimilitude</hi> of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or function, which cauſeth mutuall compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19994:12"/>as all neruous partes haue with the braine: whereby if any Nerue or neruous part bee hurt or pricked, the braine ſuffreth a convulſion, or <hi>for neighbourhood</hi> and vicinitie, whereby one part may offend another, by compreſsion or incumbencie: as in the prolapſe of the Mother, the bladder or fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament is oftentimes offended in their naturall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. And in this diſeaſe which we haue in hand by the locall motion of it vpwardes, the midriffe is ſtraightned of his ſcope, whereby the lunges doe faile in their dutie, or by <hi>reaſon of connexion or conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitie</hi> which it hath with other parts, by Vaines, Nerues, Arteries, Membranes, Ligaments, &amp;c. whereby the offence is eaſily imparted vnto other partes.<note place="margin">Gal: locorum affect: <hi>1:</hi> cap. <hi>6</hi>
                  </note> Or laſtly by priuation of ſome <hi>facultie or matter,</hi> whereof the part hath neede. As in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the <hi>Spina Dorſi</hi> there followeth a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution or palſie of the legges or armes, by reaſon that the animall facultie that ſhould giue ſence or motion to the part is intercepted and hindered in his paſſage. Likewiſe in a reſolution of the Muſcles of the breſt, as in a wound of that part, or in ſwoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the voice is taken away,<note place="margin">Rondeletius cap <hi>69.</hi> Trin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cauell loco citato:</note> becauſe the matter of it which is breath, is either not ſufficiently made, or is carried another way, or not competently impel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the organs of voyce.</p>
               <p>All theſe manner of wayes hath the Matrix by conſent to impart her offence vnto other parts. For there wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth no corruption of humor, vapour, nor euill qualitie, where this part is ill affected, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect other partes withall, there wantes no oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie
<pb facs="tcp:19994:13"/>of conueyance or paſſage vnto any part, by reaſon of the large Vaynes, Arteries, and Nerues, which are deriued vnto it, with which it hath great affinitie and ſimilitude of ſubſtance, beſides the connexion it hath with the heart, liuer, braine, and backe. It is linked alſo in neighborhoode with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe partes of great vſe, as the bladder, guttes, mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe, &amp;c. which are likely to bee warmed when this part doth burne. <hi>According to the varietie of cauſes and diſeaſes wherewith the wombe is offended,</hi> theſe <hi>Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms</hi> doe differ in nature, or in degree.<note n="a" place="margin">Mercatus pag. <hi>165.</hi>
                  </note> A plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull matter produceth a vehement <hi>Symptom:</hi> a corrupt matter according to the degree of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the qualitie of the humor corrupted, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth like accidents. The diſeaſes alſo of the Mother being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plicated with the former corrupt humors do yeeld varietie of <hi>Symptoms:</hi> as the riſing of the Mother, which alwayes cauſeth ſhortnes of breath: b Empoſtumes of the Mother according to the place where they are bred,<note place="margin">Mathaeus de gradi. &amp; Aui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenna locis citatis.</note> and the quality of them, doe alſo bring a difference in <hi>Symptoms.</hi> And thus much for explanation of the definition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19994:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Cap. 3.</hi> Of the kinds of this diſeaſe, and firſt of that wherein the vitall facultie is offended.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow I come to the kinds and ſorts of this diſeaſe, which may bee reduced vnto three principall heades, according as euerie part of the bodie belongeth vnto ſome of the three principall functions which do gouerne the bodie of man. Not that euerie <hi>Symptom</hi> in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe doth hurt ſome of the three functions,<note place="margin">Affectus corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris vel excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionum vitia.</note> for ſome are onely moleſtations or deformities, as ſudden Collickes, windie humors, noyſes, alteration of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, &amp;c. But becauſe euerie part may well bee mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred vnder ſome of theſe generals: and we doe ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſee any hyſtericall affect wherein ſome one or mo of the functions are not affected. Theſe func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as they are diſtinct in office, ſo they poſſeſſe in our bodies ſeuerall ſeats and haue ſeuerall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments belonging vnto them.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The vitall function which by preſeruing na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall heat in a due temperature, maintaineth the coniunction of ſoule and bodie togither, hath his principall manſion in the heart, and from thence by his Arteries conueyeth vitall ſpirites vnto euery member. So as without this wee could not liue: and therefore it is accounted the principalleſt func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:19994:14"/>becauſe the reſt receyue their being from this, and this fayling they muſt needes all ceaſe. This function is performed by the motion of the heart, and Arteries, which in this affect of the Mother is drawne into conſent as it is either diminiſhed, abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, or depraued. The deprauation of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is either when it is too faſt and quick, or when it beates diſorderly. The pulſe in this diſeaſe is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes too quicke, although it bee weake with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: but ſeeing it brings no great offence with it, the patient doth ſeldome complaine therof. The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter offence is when it beates diſorderly, and keepes no equall nor orderly ſtroke, but either trembleth and daunceth in the motion, or elſe is violently im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled: inſomuch as it doth not onely remoue ones hande being applied to ſome part where the Arteries are great,<note place="margin">Trincauel. li. <hi>4</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> and neare to the skinne) as lately appeared in a noble Gentleman of this lande now dead) but as <hi>Fernelius</hi> teſtifieth, hath ſometimes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed the ribbes,<note place="margin">De partium morbiset ſymp. lib. <hi>5:</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> and ſometimes broken them through the violent motion of the heart.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Symptom</hi> is called the palpitation or bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the heart, or Arteries whereof <hi>Maximillian</hi> the Emperour died as <hi>Crato</hi> reporteth, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Charles</hi> the fift was oftentimes moleſted, as <hi>Veſalius</hi> writeth. It is chiefly to bee perceyued where the Arteries are great &amp; neare the skin: as vnder the left ribbes towards the backe, and in the necke: as you may obſrue in Maides that haue the greene ſickeneſſe, by the ſhaking and quiuering of their ruffes, if they ſit cloſe to their neckes: where ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19994:14"/>through the dilatation of the Arterie there ariſeth a<note n="a" place="margin">Aneuriſma. Pernel. loeo citato.</note> tumour as bigge as ones fiſt. This <hi>Symp tom</hi> is euerie where mentioned by our<note n="b" place="margin">Petrus Salius pag. <hi>429.</hi> Skinckius de cordis palpit. abſ. <hi>211.</hi> item <hi>218.222.</hi> Foreſtus lib. <hi>17</hi> obſ. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> Authours in this diſeaſe and our dayly experience confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it.</p>
               <p>This motion of the heart and Arteries in this affect of the Mother is oftentimes diminiſhed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in part or to ſenſe totally. In part, where the pulſe in this diſeaſe is weake, ſlow, obſcure, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittent, &amp;c. and the whole bodie accordingly fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſlow in euery action, for want of influence of vitall facultie from the heart. It is totally dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in that <hi>Symptom</hi> which is called <hi>Syncope</hi> or ſwounding, the very image of death, where the pulſe is<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. loc, affect. <hi>6.</hi> c <hi>5.</hi> pulſum vix perceptibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem habent &amp;c Item de compox ſit. pharmac. ſ.l. lib. <hi>9</hi> in finit.</note> ſcarcely or not at all perceyued; the breath or reſpiration cleane gone: by reaſon that the heart wanting his motion, hath no neede of the helpe of the lungs to refreſh it withall, all the faculties of the body fayling, it ſelflying like a dead corpſe three or foure houres togither, and<note n="d" place="margin">Antho. Guay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerius. cap. de ſuffoc. matrici<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Albert, Botio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus loco infra citato. Gal. loco citato. Altomarus loco citato.</note> ſometimes two or three whole dayes without ſenſe, motion, breath, heate, or any ſigne of life at all (like as wee ſee Snakes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures to lie all the winter, as if they were dead, vnder the earth) inſomuch as diuerſe<note n="e" place="margin">Ambroſ. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeus li. <hi>24.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> errors haue beene committed in laying foorth ſuch for dead, which haue afterwards beene found to haue life in them, and haue riſen vp in their burials, whereupon there haue beene lawes enacted, as<note n="f" place="margin">De morbis muliebr: lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi> Iacobus Syluius de menſibus mulierum.</note> 
                  <hi>Mercurialis</hi> reporteth, that no woman which was ſubiect to this diſeaſe ſhould be buried vntil ſhe had beene three dayes dead. Or as<note n="g" place="margin">De morbis medicandis. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Alexander Benedictus</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19994:15"/>of <hi>Bolonia</hi> ſayth 72. houres, which commeth to the ſame reckoning.<note n="a" place="margin">Practicae lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Petrus Bayrus</hi> ſetteth downe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe reaſons why they ſhould not be buried before three dayes bee ended, beſides the experience of ſome (as hee ſaith) that haue beene found aliue in their graues after they had beene buried. I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the reader for the reaſons to the author himſelf, and to<note n="b" place="margin">Lib. <hi>10.</hi> obſer. <hi>79.</hi> in ſcholiis.</note> 
                  <hi>Forrestus</hi> in his obſeruations.<note n="c" place="margin">Hiſtor. nat. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>52.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Plinie</hi> maketh mention out of <hi>Heraclides,</hi> of a woman who for ſeuen dayes together lay for dead in a fit of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and was reſtored againe to life: which (ſaieth<note n="d" place="margin">De medica hyſtoria mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili. lib. <hi>4.</hi> ca.<hi>11</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Marcellus Donatus</hi>) is not to be thought a fabulous tale, ſeeing it is not repugnant to the rules of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie and Phiſicke. And<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>6.</hi> Locorum affect. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Galen</hi> making mention of the verie ſame hyſtorie vnder the name of <hi>Apnaea,</hi> diſcourſeth of the reaſons of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. Schinckius refert ex picto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio. obſeruat. med. lib <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>288.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Rabbi Moſes</hi> an ancient Author in Phyſicke, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth alſo of a woman, that in the fitte of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, did lie ſix dayes without ſenſe and motion, her Arteries being waxt hard, and ſhe readie to be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and yet recouered.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Demorbis muliebribus cap. <hi>43.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bottouus</hi> a late profeſſor of Phyſicke in Padua, reporteth of a woman that beeing giuen ouer for dead in a fit of the Mother, was by ſuch concluſions as he tried, diſcouered to be yet aliue, and recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her former health againe by ſuch remedies as he preſcribed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Obſeru. li. <hi>10.</hi> in ſcholiis ad obſeruat. <hi>79.</hi> Iacobus Ruffius teſtatur ſe plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res huiuſmod. vidiſſ. mulieb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. <hi>6,</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Foreſtus</hi> of <hi>Alkmar</hi> in north <hi>Holland,</hi> but lately dead, ſetteth downe the like example of another, that lay in that maner 24. houres, and was by him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to health againe.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19994:15"/>
               <p>The like alſo he citeth out of <hi>Leouellus,</hi> in that place, of one that lay with her eyes ſhut, and dumb a whole day, and by conuenient remedies was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from her fit, and could rehearſe all that was done about her in the time of her fit. But the moſt pitifull example of all other in this kinde,<note place="margin">De hominis ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerat. cap. <hi>46.</hi>
                  </note> is that which <hi>Ambroſe Paraee</hi> reporteth of <hi>Veſalius</hi> a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Phyſition, &amp; for anatomicall diſſections much renowmed, who being called to the opening of a Gentlewoman in Spaine, which was thought to be dead through the violence of one of theſe fits, began to open her, and at the ſecond cut of the knife ſhe cried out, and ſtirred her limbes, ſhewing manifeſt ſignes of life to remaine. The beholders were exceedingly amazed at the ſight, and blamed the Phyſition much for it: who though hee tooke her for dead, yet tooke he great apprehenſion of ſorrow for that accident, that he eſtranged himſelfe. After through griefe and remorſe of conſcience for his error, pretended (as others ſay) a pilgrimage for the abſenting of himſelfe, and therein died. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more examples to this end could I produce out of <hi>Authenticall</hi> writers, and late experiences, if it were free for mee to mention them: but theſe may ſuffice to ſhew how wonderfully the vitall facultie is ouerthrowne in this diſeaſe, and withall reſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſenſe, motion, and all the functions of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die by reaſon of this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19994:16"/>
               <head>Cap. <hi>4.</hi> Of that kind of this diſeaſe wherein the animall facultie is offended.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſecond kind of this diſeaſe is, where the animall facultie doth principally ſuffer; and it is that faculty whereby we do vnderſtand, iudge, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber things that are profitable or hurtfull vnto vs, whereby alſo we haue ſence and do feele the qualities of things, and moue to and fro, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme diuers other voluntary actions for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of the bodie. For nature had made vs but baſe creatures, if ſhe had giuen vs onely the vitall facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie barely to liue, and the naturall to grow, and to ſupply the expence that is daily made of naturall moiſture: If ſhe had not withall giuen vs knowledg and vnderſtanding of ſuch things as we are ſubiect vnto, and abilitie to moue our bodies at our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to apprehend that which is profitable &amp; to ſhun that which is offenſiue, &amp;c. And therefore as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie making moſt for the dignitie and vſe of man, it is placed principally in the braine; from whence it diſperſeth his beames of influence into euery part of the bodie, according to the ſeuerall vſes and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie of each part.</p>
               <p>This animall facultie hath this peculiar difference from the vitall and naturall faculties, that the functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19994:16"/>of it are ſubiect vnto our wil, &amp; may be inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded remitted, or peruerted at our pleaſure, otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the other faculties: For no man can make his pulſe to beate as he liſt, or alter the naturall functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at his will and pleaſure. But theſe animall func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be abuſed both by our owne will, and by the violence of ſome diſeaſe, and by both, as <hi>Galen</hi> teſtifieth, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Symptomatum cauſis cap.</hi> 12. That it may be abuſed by our owne will, he proueth alſo in another place,<note place="margin">De motu muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culorum lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>7.8.</hi>
                  </note> where he bringeth an inſtance of a ſeruant <hi>(ſerui barbari)</hi> who killed himſelfe to anger his maiſter by holding of his breath. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith that he knew a man that could make himſelfe to ſweate when he liſt, by his imagnation only.<note place="margin">De ciuitate Dei lib. <hi>4:</hi> Coſmocrit. lib. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> pag. <hi>156.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius Gemma</hi> ſaith, that he knewe one that could weepe when he liſt: others that could make their bodies ſtiffe like an image, imitate the voyces of all kinde of creatures, raiſe a hickocke, and breake wind as often and in what maner they would. And S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tels of one that would make a kinde of muſicke that way.<note place="margin">Medici pariſien ſes in hiſtoria Martha. Broſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier.</note> 
                  <hi>Adrian Turnebus</hi> ſaw a rogue that gayned much money by ſhewing this feate, we do alſo daily ſee that ſome can counterſait madnes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1. Sam. 21.13.</hi> Gal. lib quomo do deprehendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur qui aegrota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſefingunt. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> ſome drunkenneſſe, ſome the falling ſickneſſe, ſome palſies and trembling, ſome can play the fooles and ſupply the roomes of innocents, ſome can make noyſes &amp; ſpeake in their bellies or throates, as thoſe which <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> calleth <hi>Eugaſtrimuthoi ventri loqui,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idemiorum. <hi>5.</hi> R. Scot. lib. <hi>7:</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> ſuch as was the holy maid of Kent, and <hi>Mildred</hi> of weſtwall, &amp;c. And it is ſtrange to ſee how young bodies will be bowed and writhed diuerſly, as wee
<pb facs="tcp:19994:17"/>ſee in tumblers iuglers, and ſuch like companions. Hereupon diuers haue counterfaited diſeaſes as I once ſaw a poor fellow being areſted for a ſmal debt cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfaited a fit of the falling ſicknes, with ſtrange and violent motions: whereby the creditor in compaſsion was moued to releaſe him. Being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed he was well againe, and vnto his friendes ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to confeſſe the couſonage: others haue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfaited poſſeſsions, either vpon meere deceit or inticed therto through the conceite of ſome diſeaſe wherewith they haue beene troubled. But for this point I referre you to the hiſtories of <hi>Agnes Brigs, Rachel Pinder,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>16.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Martha Broſsier,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ren. Scot</hi> tels of one that being blind, deafe, and dumbe, could reade any canonicall Scripture, but no Apocripha: But was diſcouered by inſerting a leafe of Apocrapha: among the canonicall. Another faining her ſelfe to be poſſeſſed with a diuell, would anſwere to any queſtion made in Engliſh, but vnderſtood no latine. Diuers ſuch like examples might bee procured to ſhew how the animall functions may be abuſed by our owne will. But againſt our willes this faculty doth ſuffer by conſent in the ſuffocation of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diuerſly according to the varietie of offices or functions which it performeth.</p>
               <p>The functions of it are three, the firſt is called <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall</hi> and principall ſence which doth gouerne and direct all the reſt by <hi>Imagination, Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory:</hi> which if it bee hurt either by imminution or deprauation or total aboliſhment, then the inferior functions doe neceſſarily participate with the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19994:17"/>They are hurt by Imminution when a man doth not <hi>Conceiue, Iudge,</hi> or remember ſo well as hee ought to doe, as in dulneſſe or blockiſhneſſe,<note place="margin">Hebetudo men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> as wee call it in vndiſcretion, fooliſhnes or want of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Imprudentia obliuio.</note> in obliuion or forgetfulnes, &amp;c. They are abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed either in thoſe drowſie affects which wee call <hi>Caros, Coma, veternus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sopor.</note> 
                  <hi>Lethargus</hi> &amp;c. or in thoſe aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing <hi>Symptoms</hi> wherein all the animall faculties are at once taken away, ſometimes with a generall reſolution or palſie, as in <hi>Apoplexies:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoplexia. Epilepſia.</note> ſometimes with a generall conuulſion, as in the falling ſicknes: ſometimes with a <hi>Stifneſſe or congelation</hi> of the body,<note place="margin">Catalepſis.</note> wherein they lie like an image in the ſame forme they were taken.</p>
               <p>Theſe internall ſences are ouerthrowne either in part or in whole in this ſuffocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the mother:<note n="a" place="margin">Hypp. de mor bis muliebr. lib <hi>1</hi> et <hi>2.</hi> Torpor oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupat caput me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s percellitur et improba fit non facile intel ligit. De virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num morbis cor fatuum fit, ex fatuitate tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por.</note> and thereupon it is likened vnto theſe former diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: and this kind is accounted by <hi>Auicen</hi> to be the moſt grieuous of all other, where the imagination and reaſon is hurt: and the other which holds them with conuulſions, contractions, &amp;c. he accounts to bee the milder and the more vſuall. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaith that commonly they can remember what was done about them in their fit:<note place="margin">Gal. loc. affect. <hi>6.5.</hi> De compo ſit. pharm. ſ. L. lib. <hi>9.</hi> in fine Rhaſis contine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e <hi>22.</hi> Eginet a. li. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>71.</hi> Aeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us tetr. <hi>4</hi> Serm <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>68.</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaliuslib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>58.</hi> Valeſcus de Taran. Iacobus Syluius Altomam. Augeni. Aui. Fen. <hi>21.3.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi> tract. <hi>4.</hi> Idem. Petr. ſalius de catelepſi. pag. <hi>384.</hi>
                  </note> vnleſſe it be of this moſt grieuous kinde.</p>
               <p>The Internall ſence is depraued when a man doth imagine, iudge, or remember thinges that are not as if they were, or things that are, otherwiſe then they are indeed. Whether they do it in cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alone, or do expreſſe it by word or deede. As
<pb facs="tcp:19994:18"/>we ſee in thoſe fooles which wee call naturals,<note place="margin">Inſania. Delirium. Melancholia. Furor.</note> in mad men, in melancholike men, in thoſe that are furious, in ſuch as do dote, in ſuch as are diſtracted through loue, feare, griefe, ioye, anger, hatred, &amp;c. In ſome of which they will laugh, crye, prattle, threaten, chide, or ſing, &amp;c. according to the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the party or the cauſe of the affect.</p>
               <p>Theſe functions are alſo depraued in too much wakefulneſſe through the commotion of the ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall ſpirits,<note place="margin">Vigilia. Inſomnium.</note> alſo in dreames, where ſomtimes beſides the deprauation of the fantaſie they wil walke, talke, laugh, crye, &amp;c. And laſtly in that diſeaſe whith is called<note n="b" place="margin">Saltus viti. F. Platerus de mentis aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione. pag. <hi>103</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Saltus Sati viti,</hi> or <hi>Saltuoſa diſpoſitio membro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> wherein they will daunce, and leape, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure to be quiet.</p>
               <p>This deprauation of the internall ſences, is ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary in the fits of the Mother, as <hi>Horatius Augenius Epiſtola.</hi> 6. ſeemes to make it of the eſſence of this diſeaſe, that the imagination is euer depraued in it. But<note n="c" place="margin">Hippocrat. de morbit virg. prae acuta infla matione inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit prae putredi ne clamat, &amp;c De morbis mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liebr. lib. 1. men re alienatur in hoc morbo et de liria fiunt furi oſa dentibus fiendet vigila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit anxia erit &amp;c. Auicen loco citato facit accidere alienationem per communitatem cerebri, &amp;c. Aetius garrulae inquietae &amp; iracundae fiunt. lib. <hi>16.7 4.</hi> Hier. mercurialis mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morborum muliebr. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> Iacobus Syluius demenſibus. Mathaeus de grad. conſilio. <hi>80.</hi> histortaem narrat furtoſi.</note> 
                  <hi>Hyppocrates, Galen, Auicen,</hi> and moſt of the beſt Authors in our profeſsion, do affirme that very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten there happeneth an alienation of the minde in this diſeaſe, whereby ſometimes they will waxe fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and raging depriued of their right iudgement and of reſt.</p>
               <p>The ſecond function of the animall facultie is the externall ſenſitiue function; which giueth to the eye the facultie of ſeeing, to the eare of hearing, to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19994:18"/>the tongue of taſting,<note place="margin">Priuatio viſus Auditus. Guſtus. Olfactus. Tactus.</note> to the noſe of ſmelling and to diuers parts of the bodie the power of feeling.</p>
               <p>This function in all theſe kindes is diminiſhed, depraued, or cleane aboliſhed, but eſpecially in this diſeaſe of the mother, we do obſcrue the offence which is done to the feeling facultie, when the parts are benummed or do not feele at all, or when they feele<note n="d" place="margin">Iuxta recep tam a medicis ſententiam do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorem hic inſero licetvideatur potius ad ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces corporis af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectus referen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</note> paine and offence, or when they feele things falſely and other wiſen then they are.</p>
               <p>Concerning hearing, although<note n="e" place="margin">Hyp:morb mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liebr. lib. o. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligo ante oculos obuerſatur et vertigo, oculi non acutevide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nihil olfaciunt vocata non au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Rhaſis <hi>22.</hi> cont. in hac paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſione non audit quando datur in auribus eius vox terribilis Aegineta loco citato. Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum ſen sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus apprehenſio &amp;c. Auicen narrat plurimum eius quod fuit in ea niſi ſit maxima et immoderata Aetius ſenſus et motus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiuntur. Gal. immobiles ſine ſenſu race<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Horatius Angenius Epiſt. <hi>6,</hi> Gal. de motu muſc. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. 6. et <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hyppoc. Rhaſis</hi> and diuers others doe obſerue that ſometimes it is hindred: yet it ſeemes to be in the former kinde where the internall facultie doe ſuffer. For <hi>Merca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> puts it as a difference from the falling ſicknes, that in this ſuffocation of the matrix they doe common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heare. The priuation of the other ſences of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, taſting, ſmelling and feeling, are verie ordinarie in this diſeaſe, as you may obſerue in the Hiſtories following, and in theſe quotations.</p>
               <p>The third function is that which giues mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the whole bodie. This motion ſerueth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for a voluntary vſe onely, or for a naturall vſe alſo. The motions for the voluntary vſe are the free motions of the externall members of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: as to bowe the whole bodie and the head by meanes of the backe, to apprehend with the hand, to ſtand and goe with the feete and legges, to chewe with the iawes, to open &amp; ſhut the lips &amp; eyelids, to moue the eies, &amp;c. This functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is <hi>diminiſhed</hi> in that affect which we cal <hi>laſsitudo,</hi> werines or vnweldines,
<pb facs="tcp:19994:19"/>wherein we are not able to moue ſo ſtrongly and nimbly as we ſhould.</p>
               <p>It is <hi>aboliſhed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Paralyſis.</note> either by a <hi>reſolution</hi> or <hi>palſie</hi> where the ſound part drawes the ſickly part, that is the part reſolued, &amp; depending draws the muſcles &amp; nerues &amp;c. or by a <hi>Spaſmus</hi> or <hi>contractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> of them<note n="g" place="margin">Contract io. platerus. Gal. de cauſis morboru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. 7. et loc. affect. li. 34.</note> where the ſick part drawes the ſound part, that is, the muſcle which is affected, drawes the member which is wel.</p>
               <p>A reſolution or palſie is either generall of both ſides of the bodie<note n="h" place="margin">Petrus Salius pag. <hi>401.</hi> tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam leuis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poplexia Fern. de part. mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis &amp; ſympt. li. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> exempting the head, or of one ſide called <hi>Haemiplegia,</hi> or yet more particular of the hand, legge, finger, &amp;c. called<note n="i" place="margin">Gal. <hi>1.</hi> prorhet com. <hi>2.50.</hi> et com. <hi>3.26.</hi> de victus rat. tom. <hi>4.27.</hi> de morb. vulg. com. <hi>2.56</hi> Gybbut. Triſmos. Tortura oris. Strabiſmus. Spaſmus Cyni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</note> 
                  <hi>parapligia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Contraction</hi> or <hi>Spaſmus</hi> is alſo of like ſortes, ſometimes the bodie is held vpright and cannot be bowed any way in that affect which is called <hi>Teta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos,</hi> ſometimes it is bowed forwardes <hi>Emproſtotonos</hi> ſometimes backward <hi>Opiſtotonos,</hi> ſomtimes the back is crookt in ſome part of it, as in <hi>Gibbo,</hi> ſometimes the iawes, lips, face, eyelids, &amp;c. are contracted, wherby they make many ſtrange faces and mouthes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as though they laughed or wept, ſometimes holding their mouthes open or awry, their eyes ſtaring, &amp;c. Sometimes the handes, armes, legges, fingers, toes, &amp;c. are contracted, ſometimes particular muſcles in the ſides, backe, armes, legs, &amp;c. one or more at once, as in crampes.</p>
               <p>It is <hi>depraued</hi> where the motions are immoderate, peruerſe, inordinate, or indece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as when they are <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quiet,</hi> &amp; cannot abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> motions and geſtures, caſting their armes and legges to and fro, vp and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19994:19"/>downe, dauncing, capring, vawting, fencing, and in diuerſe maners forming their motions.<note place="margin">Marcellus Doc natus. li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. 4</note> Alſo in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions</hi> of the members, where they are ſhaken and pulled by inordinate motions, as wee ſee in the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſickneſſe. Alſo in <hi>trembling, palpitation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Felix Platerus de motu depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uato. pag. <hi>401.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>rigor</hi> where the teeth do chatter, horror where the haire ſtandes vpright, ſtretching, yawning, gaſping twinckling of the eyes, &amp;c. Theſe impediments and deprauations of motion are dayly obſerued in vterne affects: as may appeare by theſe teſtimonies. <hi>Hyppocrat. de morbi muliebr. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Albas oculorum par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſubuertit, dentibus frendet, &amp; ſimilis fit his qui hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leo morbo detinentur. Item fit co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uulſio fortis articulorum corporis, claudam facit aut impotentem prae rigore, alias atque alias ſeipſam iactabit. Horror. Erectae ceruicis ſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ipſam tenet, &amp; quicquidederit aut biberit ipſam mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtat. Torpor occupat manus &amp; inguina, &amp; crura &amp; pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites. Magnis pedum digitis conuelluntur gybboſa fit, de nat. muliebr. Gal. lib. de ſemine cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Tenſiones lumbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; manuum, &amp; pedum viduam apprehendebant loc. affect.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Aliis crura &amp; bracchia contrahuntur. Aui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenna. minor ſuffocationum eſt quae facit accidere ſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum &amp; tetanum, ſine nocumento in ratione &amp; ſenſu. Quandoque claudit oculos &amp; non aperit eos. Stridor den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, percuſsio oculorum, &amp; motus inuoluntarius lacerto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Rhaſis. Stridor dentium cum ſpaſmo &amp; torquedine extremitatum, dolores fortes adeo vt mulierem torquere faciant vndique &amp; caput genibus implicari. &amp;c. Meſue loco ſuperius citato. Aetius. Oculi poſt multam grauitatem attolluntur, vterus paulatim laxatur &amp; intellectum &amp; ſenſum recipit. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19994:20"/>
               <p>The animall motions which doe ſerue for na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall vſe, haue their power from the animall facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but their vrging and prouoking and cauſe from the naturall, and are either <hi>Reſpiration, Ingeſtion, or Excretion.</hi> Reſpiration hath annexed vnto it voyce, and ſpeach,<note place="margin">Suffocatio. Anthon. Guay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerius. cap. de ſuffocatione.</note> this is diminiſhed or aboliſhed in <hi>Suffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> or choaking, from whence this diſeaſe which we intreat of taketh his name, as from the moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Symptom</hi> which appeareth in it.<note place="margin">Priuatio vocis.</note> In <hi>difficulty</hi> of breathing. In priuation of <hi>voyce and ſpeach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is depraued when it is done immoderately or inordinately, whether it be voluntarie, or inuolun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, as in <hi>ſhortneſse of breath, ſighing, yawning, the hic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kock, ſneeſing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cita reſpiratio, ſuſpirtum. Oſcitatio. Singultus. Sternuta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io, Ructus, tuſsis. Deglutitio. Excret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o.</note> 
                  <hi>coughing, belching, vomiting, making of noyſes, blowing, and reaching, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ingeſtion, or ſwallowing,</hi> is alſo hurt in this affect, when either they cannot ſwallow meate, or drinke at all, or with great difficultie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Excretion</hi> is alſo hurt in this caſe, by vomit, ſeege or vrine, &amp;c. when either they cannot performe it being prouoked, or do it out of ſeaſon, or more then is conuenient. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Symptoms</hi> alſo appeare in the Suffocation of the Mother. <hi>Hyppocrat. de nat. muliebri. Muta de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repentè fit. de morbis muliebr. linguaipſius refrenatur &amp; hanc non claram habet. Aliquibus etiam vocis priuatio. Spiritus ſublimis it, et ſuffocatio et anhelatio denſa ipſam corripit. De nat. muliebr. Tuſſis detinet &amp; contabiſcit &amp; videtur peripnumonia eſſe, &amp;c. Gal. 9. de compiſ. Ph. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. aliquibus voxintercipitur. loc. affect. 6.5. aliae inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptas habent ſpirationes aliae ſuffocationes, &amp;c. Hyppoc.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19994:20"/>de nat. muliebr. quicquid ederit autbiberit ipſam moleſtat. Auicen. Abſcinditur loquela &amp;c. Rhaſis. Strictura anhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litus, ſquinantia, peripneumonia, apoſlema in gutture ex co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municatione Diaphragmatis cummatrice. Gal. Loco ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tato humiditas quaedam ê locis muliebribus excurrit. &amp;c. Rondalat. cap. 69. Hollerius. cap. 59. Syluius ſuſpirium. Montagnana conſilio.</hi> 225.</p>
               <p>Theſe motions as they belong to the animall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie are principally hurt by <hi>Reſolution, contraction,</hi> or <hi>conuulſion,</hi> according as the ſimple motions are, and therefore we ſhall not need to ſtand any longer vppon them in this place: as they belong vnto the naturall facultie, and do receyue offence in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſhall be declared hereafter in the third general faculty. In the mean time let vs produce ſome exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of this 2. kind of <hi>Suffocation,</hi> where the animall faculty doth principally ſuffer: for examples many times do perſwade more then doctrine.<note place="margin">De morbis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternis lib. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>59.</hi> in ſcholiis.</note> 
                  <hi>Hollerius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth that the gouernour of <hi>Roan</hi> in France had two daughters which were helde with theſe fits, in ſuch ſort as they would laugh an houre or two to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, and confeſſed that they could not refraine from laughing, although diuerſe means to that end were vſed, both by entreaty, and by threates. He tels alſo of a gentlewoman <hi>de Rochpot,</hi> who being in theſe fits would raue, laugh, &amp; weep,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 28. <hi>obſeris</hi> 26.</note> her eies being ſhut. <hi>Foreſtus</hi> maketh mention of one <hi>Alcida Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici at Alkmare</hi> a yong luſty maid who was held 24. houres in a moſt grieuous fit of the mother, wherin ſhe lay as if ſhe had beene halfe dead, hearing what was ſaid about her, but could not ſpeake, nor enioy
<pb facs="tcp:19994:21"/>her other ſenſes. Sometimes ſhe would bee pulled as if ſhe had the falling ſickeneſſe, ſometimes would lie ſtill as if ſhe were in an <hi>Apoplexie,</hi> ſometimes ſhe would onely ſtirre her legges,<note place="margin">Aliam egregia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> motuum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ab vtero byſtor. vide apud eundem. li. <hi>10.</hi> obſer. <hi>116</hi> Lib. <hi>26.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> the reſt of her bodie being dull: and although ſhe could not ſpeake, yet ſhe would crie and laugh by turnes, and then be ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len and dumpiſh, as if ſhe were dead againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander Benedictus veronenſis</hi> teſtifieth, that he ſaw a woman in a fit of the Mother, that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides her ſelfe, and would ſometimes laugh &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times crie. Thoſe that attended her, applied Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trige feathers vpon coales vnto her noſtrilles, and by chance through want of care there fell a great coale out of the Chafingdiſh into her boſome, where it burnt her, and made a great bliſter, but ſhe percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it not vntill the next day, and then complained of her breaſts. My ſelfe had a patient in this Citie yet liuing and in good health (whome I will name vnto any whome it may concerne) that endured a violent fitte of the Mother a whole day together: wherein ſhee had many ſtrong conuulſions, and ſometimes did lie as if ſhe had beene dead. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the midwiues would haue giuen her ouer, and imputed ignorance vnto mee that I woulde attempt any thing for her recouerie. But her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band being perſwaded by me to make triall of ſome meanes which I had preſcribed for her, ſhee was within three or foure houres deliuered of a childe; yet knew not of it, vntill ſhee was throughly reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered of her fit, which was fourteene or fifteene houres after, and then ſhe asked her husband what
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19994:21"/>was become of her great bellie. I could rehearſe two other ſuch like examples within this citie, which happened not many moneths ſince.</p>
               <p>But we had of late a moſt rare example of this diſeaſe in an Eſſex Gentlewoman of good note, who being once frighted by ſquibs, fell into theſe fits of the Mother, which held her euery day, and whenſoeuer elſe ſhe did eate any comfortable meat, for the ſpace of fifteene or ſexteene yeares togither, with ſuch violent conuulſions, as fiue or ſix ſtrong men could ſcarce hold her downe. Sometimes her limbes would be contracted, ſometimes perticular Muſcles, which would cauſe ſwellings in diuerſe parts of her bodie, ſometimes ſhe would be without all maner of ſenſe. And being made beleeue by a ſtranger Phyſition that ſhe was bewitched, her fits increaſed vpon her, and grew to bee ſtronger then before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bartholomeus Montagnana</hi> reciteth vp 31. ſeuerall <hi>Symptoms</hi> of this diſeaſe which hee obſerued in a Gentlewoman which was his patient. Conuulſions, ſwoundings, choaking in the throate, ſadneſſe and lamentation, coldnes ouer her whole bodie, dumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and yet could heare, drowſineſſe, beating of the heart, trembling of the handes, contraction of the fingers, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It were in vaine to heape vp many examples to this purpoſe, ſeeing our daily experience doth yeeld vs ſufficient ſtore of proofe of the varietie of theſe <hi>Symptoms</hi> in the animall facultie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19994:22"/>
               <head>Cap. 5. Of that kind wherein the naturall facultie is offended.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He third kinde of this diſeaſe is, where the naturall facultie doth principally ſuffer. This facultie is of great neceſsitie for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of mankinde and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diuerſe vſes thereof is diſtinguiſhed. For ſeeing that nature bringes vs not forth into the world perfect men, in that ripeneſſe and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, of all humaine actions which afterwards we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto, when wee come to full growth, it was meete to be prouided of ſuch a facultie in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies as might encreaſe ourſtature, &amp; ſtrengthen the inſtruments of the whole body, for the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the actions thereof. And this is called <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultas auctrix.</hi> Seeing alſo that wee are made of a fluxible moulde which waſteth and ſpendeth it ſelfe many wayes, whereby it ſtandeth in neede of continuall refection and replie: Therefore it was meete to be furniſhed with ſuch a facultie as might repaire the decay and expence of our ſubſtance, by yeelding continually apt matter for the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the bodie. And that is called <hi>facultas al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix.</hi> And thirdly ſeeing, notwithſtanding our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are continually nouriſhed with the beſt food, yet they muſt once die as well as other inferiour
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19994:22"/>creatures doe: therefore God hath indued vs as well as other creatures with the facultie of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: whereby wee may bee able to make our kind to continue as long as the world ſhall endure.</p>
               <p>Theſe three naturall faculties haue diuerſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers attending vpon them, as the faculties of <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, Retention, Concoction, Expulſion, Alteration, Formation, &amp;c.</hi> Which I will for breuitie ſake ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe with their bare mention, becauſe the <hi>Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms</hi> of theſe faculties are not ſo euident to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders eye,<note place="margin">Gal. de tremor. palp. tit. &amp;c. cap. <hi>2.</hi> ſenſibus non expoſita.</note> nor ſo ſtraunge as thoſe of the vitall and animall faculties are, yet that theſe are alſo hurt in the ſuffocation of the Mother, appeareth both by dayly obſeruation, and by the authorities of all both auncient and late phyſitions who haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of this diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Some of theſe are <hi>Symptoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta in qualitate mutata,</hi> or <hi>in excremento vitiato:</hi> but be cauſe they are in the naturall parts, and ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, I haue inſerted them here.</note>And to this place may we referre thoſe accidents often mentioned in this diſeaſe.<note n="a" place="margin">Hypp. de mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis mulieb. lib. <hi>1</hi> Rhaſis con. li. <hi>22.</hi> Fernel. de partium morb. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi> Mercatus lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>3.</hi> Bottonus, &amp; Mercurialis lociscitatis. Syluius de menſibus.</note> 
                  <hi>Gnawing in the ſtomacke,</hi> and paines in diuerſe partes of the bodie, breaking of wind, vomiting, purging by ſiege, vrin, or other excretion, loathing of meate, thirſt, extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie hunger, ſwelling in the throat, ſwelling in the body, in the feet, obſtructions in the vaines, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, tumors, feuers, priuation of voice, pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of colour, rumbling and noiſe in the belly or<note n="b" place="margin">Schenkiusobſer. deptiſiobſer. <hi>137.</hi> Cornel. Gema. Coſmocr. Hyppocrat. Epidem. <hi>5.</hi> expectore obſtrepebat. &amp;c.</note> throat, like vnto frogs, ſnakes, or other creatures, or as if they woule ſpeake as <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> reporteth of <hi>Polymarchus</hi> wife.</p>
               <p>And theſe are three principall kindes of this
<pb facs="tcp:19994:23"/>diſeaſe wherevnto moſt of the <hi>Symptoms</hi> which euer do appeare therein may be referred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Cap. 6.</hi> Of the cauſes of this diſeaſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He cauſes of this diſeaſe and of the <hi>Symptoms</hi> belonging therunto, haue euer bin found hard to be deſcribed particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly: and eſpecially in a vulgar tongue, I hold it not meete to diſcourſe to freely of ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and therefore I doe craue pardon if I do but ſlenderly ouerpaſſe ſome poynts which might be otherwiſe more largely ſtood vpon</p>
               <p>The cauſes of this diſeaſe are either internall, or externall. The internall cauſes may be any thing contained within the bodie, as ſpirit, blood, humors excrements, &amp;c. whereby this part is apt to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, but principally they are referred vnto theſe two,<note n="a" place="margin">Gal. loc. affec. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> Holle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, demorbis internis. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>59.</hi> Paſchalius li. <hi>1</hi> cap. <hi>57.</hi> Altomarus. ea. <hi>1 10.</hi> Item de vtero gerenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. cap. <hi>2.</hi> Iacobus Sylutus de menſibus. Hor. Augenius epict. <hi>6.</hi> Cardanus de cauſis, &amp;c. morborum. cap. <hi>114.</hi>
                  </note> blood, and nature.</p>
               <p>Blood is that humor wherwith we are nouriſhed: without which the infant in the mothers wombe could neither grow &amp; increaſe in bigneſſe, nor yet liue: and therefore it was neceſſarie that thoſe that were fit for generation, ſhould be ſupplied with ſufficient ſtore of this humor, for the vſe of this part wherin the infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is to be nouriſhed, for which cauſe there are large vaines &amp; arteries deriued vnto it for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19994:23"/>the conueyance of bloud thereunto, and there is greater prouiſion thereof made in womens bodies then in mens: leaſt this part ſhould bee forced to withdraw nouriſhment from other parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and ſo leaue them weake and conſuming.</p>
               <p>But this prouiſion of nature is oftentimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue: as when it is cut off by violent cauſes,<note place="margin">Defectus.</note> and the part left deſtitute of this familiar humor, which ſhould ſerue both for the comfort of the infant, and of the part it ſelfe: which finding offence thereby doth communicate it vnto the other partes with which it hath affinitie according to <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. <hi>1. Morborum muliebrium,</hi> and <hi>Aristotle, de gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. animal.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hollerius et Rondelet. loci citatis. Comment. <hi>2.</hi> in lib. <hi>1.</hi> Hypp. de morb. muliebr.</note> 
                  <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>vteri cuacuati ſurſum aſcendunt &amp; praefocationes faciunt. Cordaeus</hi> giues vs an example of one who by chaunce cutting a vaine in her leg, whereupon ſhe did bleede plentifully, fell into a fit of the Mother, and by moiſt and nouriſhing diet was recouered. The reaſon whereof <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> referreth to the ouerdrying of thoſe parts through large euacuatiou of bloud, wherby the matrix doth labour by ſuch motion as it hath to ſupply it ſelfe with moyſture from other parts of the body: or as <hi>Mercurialis</hi> doth enterpret it,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 22.</note> doth impart by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie (as is aforeſaid) the offenſiue qualitie vnto the braine, and by that meanes procures convulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp;c. <hi>Gallen</hi> referreth it vnto the ouercooling of thoſe parts which neceſſarily muſt follow a large euacuation of bloud,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> loc. affect.</note> which coldeneſſe being very offenſiue vnto the nerues and neruous partes by conſent and compaſsion offendeth the braine alſo,
<pb facs="tcp:19994:24"/>and by that meanes may procure the former <hi>Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as the want and ſcarſitie of bloud may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure this griefe,<note place="margin">Receſſui.</note> ſo the abundance &amp; exceſſe thereof doth more commonly cauſe it, where the patients do want thoſe monethly euacuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which ſhould diſcharge their bodies of this ſuperfluitie: as we ſee in ſtrong and luſtie maidens, who hauing eaſe and good fare inough, haue their vaines filled with plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of bloud,<note place="margin">Gal. loc. affect. <hi>6</hi> Pered a in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chalium lib. <hi>I.</hi> cap. <hi>58.</hi> Altomarus. Syluius.</note> which wanting ſufficient vent diſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth them in bulck and thicknes, and ſo contracteth them in their length, whereby the matrix is drawne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards or ſidewards, according as the repletion is, whereupon followeth a compreſsion of the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour parts, as of the midrif which cauſeth ſhortnes of breath, by ſtraightning the inſtruments of reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their due ſcope.</p>
               <p>But if this bloud wanting his proper vſe doe degenerate into the nature of an excrement, then it offendeth in qualitie as well as in exceſſe, and being detayned in the bodie, cauſeth diuers kinds of <hi>Symptoms,</hi> according to the qualitie and degree of the diſtemperature thereof.</p>
               <p>This diſtemperature is either in manifeſt quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, of heate,<note place="margin">Alteratio.</note> colde, moiſture, drines, according vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which it is ſaid to be,<note place="margin">Hypp. de morbis vir ginum. Altomarut Corruptio.</note> 
                  <hi>Melancholicke, Flegmaticke, Choloricke, &amp;c.</hi> producing <hi>Symptoms</hi> of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or in corruption and putrefactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this bloud which breedeth diuers ſtrange kinds of diſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">Mercatus loco citato.</note> according to the diuerſity of the humor pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefied, the degree of putrefaction or the condition
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19994:24"/>of the cauſe or author thereof.</p>
               <p>The other ſubſtance which moſt commonly is found culpable of this diſeaſe, is nature or <hi>ſperma:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rondeletius c. <hi>69.</hi> Platerus. Pereda in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chalia. Valeſius de Tar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant a. lib <hi>6.</hi> Velaſiusteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſe deprehen deſſe circa vte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> byſtericaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> croceum humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem faetidiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c. lib. <hi>5.6.15.</hi> Mathaus de grad. in. <hi>9.</hi> Rha ſis. ca. <hi>28.</hi> Item conſilio <hi>84.</hi> Mercatus. Gal. Auicen. Mercurialis. Bottonus locis citatis. Hercules Saxo nia de plica. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>14.</hi> et. <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note> which beſides the ſuſpition of ſuperfluitie in ſome perſons, may alſo receiue diuers ſortes of alteration, and likewiſe of corruption, able to worke moſt ſtrange and grieuous accidents in our bodies. For as it is a ſubſtance of greateſt perfection &amp; puritie ſo long as it retayneth his natiue integritie: So being depraued or corrupted, it paſſeth all the humors of our bodie, in venom and malignitie. For it muſt needs be a vehement and an impure cauſe that ſhal corrupt ſo pure a ſubſtance, which would eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt any weake aſſault: and a ſubſtance ſo pure and full of ſpirits as this is, muſt needes proue moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious vnto the bodie when it is corrupted. And therefore it is compared to the venom of a ſerpent, a Scorpion, a Torpido, a madde dogge, &amp;c. which in a ſmall quantirie is able to deſtroy or depraue all the faculties of our bodies at once.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galen</hi> comparing the corruption of theſe two together, affirmeth that although from the putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of bloud, diuers moſt terrible accidents doe ariſe, yet they are not ſo deadly as thoſe which proceede from the corruption of nature;<note place="margin">Syluius, &amp;c.</note> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it by this obſeruation that diuers women en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying the benefit of mariage, yet through the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion of their ordinary euacuation falling into this diſeaſe, had their reſpiration and vitall facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties vntouched, although otherwiſe they were moſt grieuouſly affected.<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19994:25"/>
               <p>others alſo hauing thoſe ordinarie matters in good ſorte, yet being widdowes and taken with this grief haue felt decay in thoſe faculties as well as in the reſt.</p>
               <p>How theſe two ſubſtances by conſent may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the whole bodie according to their ſeuerall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, hath beene ſhewed before: But one ſcruple remaineth here to be diſcuſſed, namely how this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous matter may lurke ſo long in our bodies in ſilence not ſhowing it ſelf but at certaine times only.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galen</hi> in the former place declareth this by the example of a mad dogge,<note place="margin">Loc. affect. <hi>6.5.</hi> Petrus ſaliusde affect. particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haribus pa. <hi>326</hi>
                  </note> whoſe venom being recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of us, although but by the foame of his mouth, will remaine ſometimes ſixe moneths within our bodies vndiſcouered, and then hauing gotten more ſtrength and ripenes vnto it ſelfe, and opportunitie of conuaying his euil quallity vnto the parts,<note place="margin">Altomarus.</note> brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth forth to open view by diminiſhing or peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the faculties of thoſe parts. I had once a pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in Kent who feeding vpon a mad hogge which hee had killed for couetouſneſſe ſake, found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe diſtempered therewith at the firſt, but within fiue or ſixe moneths after grewſuddenly to be ſtarke madde, and before his death, being by Phiſicke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to ſome reaſonable vnderſtanding, he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the eating of that hogge to haue beene the true cauſe of his diſeaſe. Diuers reaſons may bee yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of this as well as of the fits of intermittent agues of <hi>Epilepſies,</hi> of ſweating, &amp;c. which oftentimes haue their due recourſe by the yeare, moneth, weeke, day or houre, according to the nature of the humor:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19994:25"/>which being crude expecteth his concoction in our bodies and giues no ſigne of his preſence vntill ſuch a proportion of it be digeſted and reſolued into va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours,<note place="margin">Ga. loc. affect. <hi>6</hi> Felix Platerus de cauſis febri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. pag. <hi>63. 65 66.</hi> &amp;c. Mercatus. Fernel. patho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. li. <hi>6,</hi> cap. <hi>16</hi>
                  </note> as for the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof the part affected is not able to brooke and for the weakeneſſe of the expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue facultie not able to auoide out of the bodie: but filling the vaines, arteries, and the habit of the body, is communicated to the principall parts; diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or deprauing their functions ſo long, vntill that portion of vapours be diſcuſſed through naturall heate: and ceaſing againe ſo long vntill by fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and concoction, another portion of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt humor ſhall be digeſted.</p>
               <p>The vniformitie of this humor and of the heate of concoction cauſeth the vniformitie of fits. And this is the cauſe of the due periods or circuites which oftentimes are obſerued in this diſeaſe, whereof wee haue ſpoken before: 2 according alſo to the condition of the part affected, which ſeruing as an euacuatorie to the whole bodie, is accuſtomed to ſuch kind of humors and therefore can endure them better then other parts can. And this is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe why this humor giues no ſigne of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence vntill it may communicate with the principall partes:<note place="margin">Quia multum. Quia prauum. Quia inſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> which are ſoone offended either with the plenty of thoſe vapours, or with the malignity, or with the vnwonted and vnaccuſtomed approach of them.</p>
               <p>The externall cauſes of this diſeaſe are either ſuch things as are ordinary and neceſſary for our life and which we cannot ſhun, as our meate and drink, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:19994:26"/>and reſt, ſleepe and watching, euacuation and perturbations of the minde: or ſuch things as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto vs accidentally, and may bee ſhunned by vs, as bathes, ointments, plaiſters, cloathes, ſmelles or vapours, medicines, venus, noyſes, riding, ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, ſayling, wounds, contuſions, falles, biting of venomous beaſts, &amp;c. which may be alſo referred to the former kindes. Theſe and ſuch like as they are the externall cauſes of all diſeaſes, our bodies being ſubiect to be hurt and offended by euery one of them: ſo they are oftentimes acceſſary to this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>The aire which compaſſeth our bodies and which we breath into our bodies is the occaſion of many infirmities in vs,<note place="margin">Fernel. li. <hi>1.</hi> de morboru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſis</note> if either it be diſtempered in quallitie or corrupted in ſubſtance, or ſuddenly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. And this may be the cauſe why women are more ſubiect vnto this diſeaſe at one time of the yeare then at another, according to the conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ayre: as in the winter time, by reaſon of colde and moyſt weather the humors of our bodies are increaſed and made more crude and groſe, and our pores ſtopped, whereby expiration is hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But eſpecially wee doe obſerue that breathing in of ſweete ſauours doth commonly procure theſe ſittes,<note place="margin">Mathaus de grade. Mercas. Rondel. cap. <hi>69.</hi>
                  </note> either for that the matrix by a naturall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie is delighted with ſweete ſauoures, as the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and ſpleene with ſweete meates,<note place="margin">Hier. Mercuria</note> or becauſe the animall ſpirites of the braine beeing thereby
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19994:26"/>ſtirred vp to motion, doe by conſent affect the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix with the like.</p>
               <p>And therefore wee doe eſpecially forbid that they may not ſmell vnto any ſweet thing that are ſubiect vnto this griefe:<note place="margin">Plater. pa. <hi>443</hi> lacobus Ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us de muliebri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>8</hi> Syluius Guaynerius.</note> but rather vnto euill fauoures: which as <hi>Platerus</hi> thinkes by ſtirring vp the expulſiue facultie of the matrix, are a meanes of the ſhortening of the fit.</p>
               <p>Meate and drinke is the Mother of moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, whatſoeuer the Father bee, for the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the humors of our bodies is according to that which feedes vs. And therefore it is reckoned as a principall externall cauſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> in this diſeaſe forbids ſweete and fatte meats <hi>(a dulcibus et pinguibus abſtineat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De nat mulie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri. Lib. <hi>2.</hi> obſeru. <hi>28.</hi> Hypp. libro cit a to quicquidede rit aut liberit ipſam moleſtat</note> 
                  <hi>donec ſana ſit) Forreſtus</hi> telles vs of a Bruets wife of <hi>Delft,</hi> who could neuer eate or drinke any thing that was ſweete or pleaſant but her fit would take her a freſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and thereuppon was faine to mixe wormewood with euery thing that ſhe did eate or drinke.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Eſſex</hi> Gentlewoman of whome I ſpake before,<note place="margin">Heurnius de morbis capitis pag. <hi>310.</hi>
                  </note> could neuer take any comfortable ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but ſhe was ſure to haue a fit of the mother. The reaſon of this may be the ſame which we haue alleaged of ſweet vapours.</p>
               <p>The errours about euacuation are alſo an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall cauſe of diſeaſes, and doe breed an internall cauſe afterwardes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19994:27"/>
               <p>As in this diſeaſe the want of due and monethly euacuation, or the want of the benefit of marriage in ſuch as haue beene accuſtomed or are apt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto,<note place="margin">Altomarus.</note> breeds a congeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of humors about that part, which increaſing or corrupting in the place, cauſeth this diſeaſe.<note place="margin">Hollerius cap. <hi>59.</hi> Rond. c. <hi>69.</hi>
                  </note> And therefore we do obſerue that mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and widowes are moſt ſubiect thereunto. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reſt being well ordered do preſerue health, but being diſordered do breed diſeaſes, eſpecially to much reſt and ſlothfulneſſe is a meanes of this griefe, by ingendering crudities and obſtructions in womens bodies, by dulling the ſpirits and cooling naturall heate, &amp;c. So likewiſe ſleepe and watching, the one by benumming, the other by diſsipation of the ſpirits and natural heate, may occaſion this griefe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hinc Cicero Tuſculanarum <hi>3.</hi> perturbatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes animi, mor bos appellat.</note> Laſtly the perturbations of the minde are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to blame both for this and many other diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. For ſeeing we are not maiſters of our owne affections, wee are like battered Citties without walles, or ſhippes toſſed in the Sea, expoſed to all maner of aſſults and daungers, euen to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of our owne bodies.</p>
               <p>We haue infinite examples among our<note n="a" place="margin">Plinium. Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. max. Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teranum. Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanum. Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Gellium, Krantzium.</note> Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographers,<note n="b" place="margin">Cornex lib. <hi>1</hi> conſultat. med. cap. <hi>3.</hi> Gal. <hi>2.</hi> ſympt. cauſis cap. <hi>5.</hi> de praecognit. ca. <hi>6</hi> Beniuenius.</note> and Phiſitions of ſuch as haue dyed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ioy, griefe, loue, feare, ſhame, and ſuch like per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations of the mind: and of others that vpon the ſame cauſes haue fallen into grieuous diſeaſes: as<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. in <hi>5.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſm. <hi>45.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matus luſit. Cent. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> women deliuered of their children before their time, vpon feare, anger, griefe, &amp;c. others taken with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19994:27"/>the<note n="1" place="margin">Gal. loc. affec. <hi>5.</hi> de Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico Iob. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſilio. <hi>50</hi> Matheus de grad. de proprio filio. cap. de Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepſia. Amatus luſit. cent. <hi>2.</hi> cap <hi>90.</hi>
                  </note> Falling ſickeneſſe,<note n="2" place="margin">Procopius de bello Gothorum lib. <hi>1.</hi> Amatus luſit. cent. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> Apoplexies,<note n="3" place="margin">Christoph. a Vega. li. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>14</hi> Corn. Celſus.</note> Madneſſe,<note n="4" place="margin">Gal. loco cita.</note> Swounding,<note n="5" place="margin">Aretaeus lib. <hi>1</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> Palſies, and diuerſe ſuch like infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities vpon the like cauſes.</p>
               <p>And concerning this diſeaſe whereof we doe intreate,<note n="6" place="margin">Conſilio <hi>311.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Iohannes Montanus</hi> tels vs of a patient of his, who fell into the fits of the Mother vppon iealouſie.<note n="7" place="margin">Lib. <hi>28.</hi> obſer. <hi>28.</hi> lib. <hi>10.</hi> obſeru. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Forreſtus</hi> of another, who had her fits whenſoeuer ſhee was angred: and of another that vpon loue fell into this diſeaſe. My felfe do know a Gentlewoman, who upon the ſight of one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular man would alwaies feele an vterin affect: and another that vpon feare of being chidden, or ſeeing another in the fit of the mother, would alſo fall into it herſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19994:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Cap. 7.</hi> Of the cure of this diſeaſe, ſo much as belongeth to the friends and attendants to performe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſignes of this diſeaſe, ſeeing they are drawne principally from the cauſes and <hi>Symptoms</hi> before declared ſhall not neede any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular diſcourſe, eſpecially conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the vſe of them belongeth properly to the Phyſition, to direct him in his cure. And therefore I thinke good to eaſe my ſelfe of this labour, which would bee altogither vnprofitable to the reader.</p>
               <p>Concerning the cure alſo I thinke it not meete to ſay more then may concerne the friends and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants vnto the patient to looke vnto: referring Phyſitions workes vnto Phyſitions. There are ſome things by the friendes to bee performed vnto the patient in regard of the<note n="a" place="margin">Valetius in Hollerium. c. <hi>59</hi> Valeſcius dï Taranta. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fit, &amp; ſome things in regard of the cauſe. In the fit let the bodies bee kept<note n="b" place="margin">Paſchal. li. <hi>1</hi> ca. <hi>57.</hi> Altomar.</note> vpright, ſtraight laced, and the belly &amp; throat held downe with ones hand. Let heed be taken that they hurt not themſelues by biting their fingers,<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>u Hollerius.</note> ſtriking their armes &amp; legs againſt hard things, &amp;c. apply euil ſmels to their noſtrils, and ſweet ſmels beneath<note n="c" place="margin">Rhaſis ad Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>anſor. cap. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> tie their legs hard with a garter for reuulſion ſake, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Out of the fit, in regard of <hi>Externall</hi> cauſes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue from them all occaſions of breeding or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19994:28"/>creaſing the diſeaſe: as ſweet ſauors, pleaſant meats and drinks, much reſt and ſlouthfulneſſe, &amp;c. Alſo if<note n="a" place="margin">Hollerius nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum remedium melius marito. Valeſcus de ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranta, Syluius. ſi nubilis eſt nec monialis nubat ſinon libet aut non licet nubere vtatur frigidis &amp;c. Mat. Rochius de morb. mal. cap. <hi>5.</hi> Guaynerius ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitio in hoc caſu principati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> obtinet, &amp;c.</note> diſcontinuance of any thing accuſtomed bee the cauſe of this diſeaſe, bring it into cuſtome againe: if want of any thing neceſſary for their health, let it be ſupplied,<note n="b" place="margin">Valetius in Holl. Cap. <hi>59.</hi> iſtud genus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monii non eiici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur niſi multo ieiunio. Paſchali. Si no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſsit vti viro praecibus &amp; ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuniocurabitur. Guaynerius. Curpus mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus vtatur.</note> let theirdiet be ſparing and vpon cooling things, let them vſe much faſting and prayer, and all other meanes to pull downe their bodies: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe abſtaine from egges, wine, fleſh, &amp;c. If the perturbations of the mind be any occaſion hereof, let them haue their proper remedies, as anger and iealouſie are to be appeaſed by good counſell and perſwaſions: hatred and malice by religious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, feare by incouragements, loue<note n="c" place="margin">Auicen, Fen. <hi>1 3.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi> tract. <hi>4.</hi> de Yliſco.</note> by indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing hatred, or<note n="d" place="margin">Aretaeus. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> De ſani. tuenda lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi> De ſubtilit. l. <hi>19</hi> De medica bist oria mirae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> by permitting them to enioy their deſires, &amp;c. <hi>Galen</hi> boaſteth that he did euery yeare cure many diſeaſes by this ſtratagem of moderating the perturbations of the mind by the example of <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> who deuiſed many ſongs and ridiculous paſtimes for that purpoſe. To which end alſo other phiſitions haue vſed diuers ſorts of fallacies to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter the melancholike conceits of their patients. <hi>Cardan</hi> tels of a Gentlewoman, who finding her ſelf vexed with many grieous <hi>Symptoms,</hi> imagined that the Diuell was the author thereof, and by <hi>Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus Niger</hi> was cured by procuring her ſon to make her beleeue that he ſaw three diuels in her looking glaſſe, &amp; one great one to driue them out. Another like policie <hi>Marcellus Donatus</hi> tels vs of, which a Phyſition vſed towardes the Counteſſe of <hi>Mantua,</hi> who being in that diſeaſe which we call <hi>melancholia
<pb facs="tcp:19994:29"/>Hyppocrondriaca</hi> did verily beleeue that ſhe was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched, and was cured by conueying of nayles, needles, feathers, and ſuch like things into her cloſe ſtoole when ſhee tooke phyſicke, making her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that they came out of her bodie. The like there he mentioneth alſo out of <hi>Trallian,</hi> of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who did thinke that ſhe had a ſerpent within her, and was cured by the like meanes.</p>
               <p>So that if we cannot moderate theſe perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the minde, by reaſon and perſwaſions, or by alluring their mindes another way, we may poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikely confirme them in their fantaſies, that wee may the better faſten ſome cure vpon them: as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinus Affricanus</hi> (if it be his booke which is inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among <hi>Galens</hi> workes,<note place="margin">Lib de incant. adiuratione, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>De incantatione, adiuratione &amp;c.</hi>) affirmeth, and practized with good ſucceſſe, vpon one who was <hi>impotens ad Venerem,</hi> &amp; thought himſelfe bewitched therewith, by reading vnto him a fooliſh medicine out of <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> made with a crowes gall, and oyle: whereof the patient tooke ſo great conceit, that vpon the vſe of it he preſently recouered his ſtrength and abilitie againe.</p>
               <p>The like opinion is to bee helde of all thoſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious remedies which haue crept into our profeſsion,<note place="margin">Si quis incan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationem ſibi prodeſſe confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat, qualiſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſit, cum tamen iuu. it. li. <hi>1.</hi> prox imé citato.</note> of Charmes, Exorciſmes, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtellations, Characters, Periapts, Amulets, Incenſe, Holie wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, clouts croſſed and folded ſuperſtitiouſly, repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a certaine number and forme of prayers or Aue Maries, offering to certaine Saintes, piſsing through the wedding Ring, and a hundred ſuch like toyes and gambols: which when they preuaile
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19994:29"/>in the cure of diſeaſes, it is not for any ſupernaturall vertue in them, either from God or from the diuell (although perhaps the Diuell may haue a collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall intent or worke therein, namely to drawe vs vnto ſuperſtition) but by reaſon of the confident perſwaſion which melancholike and paſsionate people may haue in them: according to the ſaying of <hi>Auicen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4. Natural. 6.</note> that the confidence of the patient in the meanes vſed is oftentimes more auailable to cure diſeaſes then all other remedies whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>Another courſe hath beene taken ſometimes in theſe caſes, by remouing the cauſe of theſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or by inducing of other perturbations of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe nature. Whereby as (experience teacheth vs) moſt grieuous diſeaſes haue beene oftentimes cured beyond expectation.</p>
               <p>A yong man falling out of fauour with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, fell thereupon into the fits of the falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and continued long and often moleſted there with; vntill a reconciliation was wrought with his father: who ſending him a kind letter to that effect, the yong man was preſently deliuered from that fearefull diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>A yong Maiden alſo vpon ſome paſſion of the minde, as it was credibly reported, fell into theſe fits of the Mother, and being in one of them, a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition then preſent modeſtly put his hand vnder her cloathes to feele a windie tumor which ſhee then had in her backe. But a Surgeon there alſo preſent not contented with that maner of examination, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to take vp her cloathes, and to ſee it bare:
<pb facs="tcp:19994:30"/>whereupon the Maid being greatly offended, tooke ſuch indignation at it, as it did put her preſently out of her fit.</p>
               <p>And it is no maruel that the affections of the mind doe beare ſuch rule in this diſeaſe, ſeeing we doe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue that moſt commonly beſides the indiſpoſition of the bodie: here is alſo ſome Melancholike or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricious conceit ioyned withall of loue, feare, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, iealouſie, diſcontentment, witchcraft, poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp;c. which being by policie or good inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and perſwaſions remoued, the diſeaſe is eaſily ouercome.</p>
               <p>Other matters of gouernment of them either in the fit or out of the fit, togither with the cure in regard of the internall cauſes, becauſe they are properly belonging to the Phyſition, I do purpoſely omit.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <p>Fol. <hi>1th.</hi> lin. <hi>22.</hi> dele one.</p>
            <p>Fol. <hi>3.</hi> a. lin. <hi>27.</hi> remoted for remoued.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19994:30"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
